<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way to glory, or, The preaching of the Gospell is the ordinary meanes of our saluation wherein is shewed what difference there is betweene the text of the Gospell, and the preaching, exposition, and glosse thereof : with a confutation of our aduersaries opinion, that the Popes defining and expounding Scriptures ex Cathedra, is to bee beleeued as vndoubted truth ... : herein also is shewed the dignity and necessity of the office of preaching the Gospell ... : preached in the Cathedrall Church of S. Paules, for the Crosse sermon, the tenth of December, 1620 / by Ro. Iohnson Bachelour of Diunity.</title>
            <author>Johnson, Ro. (Robert)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 84 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04574</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14693.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2160</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23092015</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23092015</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26209</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04574)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26209)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1797:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way to glory, or, The preaching of the Gospell is the ordinary meanes of our saluation wherein is shewed what difference there is betweene the text of the Gospell, and the preaching, exposition, and glosse thereof : with a confutation of our aduersaries opinion, that the Popes defining and expounding Scriptures ex Cathedra, is to bee beleeued as vndoubted truth ... : herein also is shewed the dignity and necessity of the office of preaching the Gospell ... : preached in the Cathedrall Church of S. Paules, for the Crosse sermon, the tenth of December, 1620 / by Ro. Iohnson Bachelour of Diunity.</title>
                  <author>Johnson, Ro. (Robert)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 45 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, and are to sold by Iohn Pyper,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 30-31 misnumbered 32-33.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26209:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26209:1"/>
            <p>The Way to Glory: <hi>OR,</hi> The preaching of the Goſpell is the ordinary <hi>meanes of our Saluation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein is ſhewed what difference there is betweene the Text of the Goſpell, and the preaching, Expoſition, and gloſſe thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With</hi> A confutation of our aduerſaries opinion, that the Popes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining and expounding Scriptures <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> is to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued as vndoubted truth, and held for the moſt certaine rule and ground of Faith.</p>
            <p>Herein alſo is ſhewed <hi>The dignity and neceſſity of the office of preaching the Goſpell, and how that Tythes and offerings are deſigned by almighty God for the ordinary maintenance thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>With</hi> A briefe confutation of all opinions repugnant to this truth.</p>
            <p>Preached in the Cathedrall Church of S. <hi>Paules,</hi> for the Croſſe Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, the tenth of December. 1620.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Ro. Iohnſon</hi> Bachelour of Diuinity.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. COR. 4 3.</bibl> If our Goſpell bee hid, it is hid to them that are loſt.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. COR. 9.14.</bibl> So alſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpell ſhould liue of the Goſpell.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON.</hi> Printed by NICHOLAS OKES, and are to be ſold by <hi>Iohn Pyper.</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:26209:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:26209:2"/>
            <head>To the moſt Reuerend Father <hi>in God,</hi> George, <hi>by the diuine</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidence, Lord Arch-biſhop of Cantur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury: <hi>Metropolitan, and Primate of</hi> all England: and one of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties moſt Honorable</hi> Priuie Councell.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Reuerend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God: your loue and zeale to the truth, haue encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged mee to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to dedicate this Sermon to your Grace: which beggeth ſhelter vnder your religious and iudicious Approbation. And the ſubiect thereof, which is the preaching of the Goſpell (againſt whoſe truth &amp; maintenance, there are ſo many oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites, which would (if they could) ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw Gods houſe, and eate vp his choſen people as they wold eate bread)
<pb facs="tcp:26209:3"/> may ſeeme iuſtly to challenge no leſſe at your hands. And the Church knows your zeale to Religion to be ſuch, that although you may bee well wearied with multitude of cauſes, yet you will neuer be deficient in vndertaking the defence of the truth: you being a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Pillar of State, and Patron of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue &amp; Iuſtice <hi>Hîc ames dici pater at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</hi> I ſuppoſe I ſhall haue both Papiſts and Schiſmatickes againſt me: it hath alwayes bin my lot hitherto, &amp; I glory in it, and paſſe not for them al, ſo I may enioy your Graces lawfull fauor to defend this truth. And ſo with my dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly prayers vnto almighty God, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tect your Grace from all dangers, and to grant you many and happy dayes:</p>
            <p>I humbly take my leaue, this 13. of Ianuary 1621.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces to be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in all duties, Robert Iohnſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26209:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, I preſent to thy view in this Sermon, two maine Subiects con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Goſpell; the one depending betwixt vs and the Papiſts,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16. Titus 1.2.</note> touching the Text of the Goſpell, which was written by the Pen-men of the holy Ghoſt, and giuen them by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration of God, in which there can bee no error or lye: and the Expoſition and gloſſe thereof, by men of mediate and ſecondary calling, in which there may be error.<note place="margin">Baron. Tom. <hi>1.</hi> annal <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> Our aduerſaries hold and mainetaine, that the Popes defining and expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Scriptures, <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> is to bee beleeued as vndoubted truth, and held for the moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine rule and ground of faith;<note place="margin">Bozius de ſig. eccleſiae pag. <hi>133</hi>
               </note> paralleling their traditions with the text of the Goſpell, and hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that their Church cannot erre in matters of faith: this is the fountaine of many ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous errors amongst them. The other touching the dignity and neceſſity of preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, with that maintenance which God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in his word to his Miniſters and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers thereof, which are tythes and offerings.
<pb facs="tcp:26209:4"/> Which truth hath bin much oppoſed in this age, by many prophane Atheiſts on the one ſide, and ſchiſmaticall ſpirits on the other ſide; which vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a colour of zeale, would, if they could, deuour Gods houſe and his Miniſters. The Apoſtle ſaith, God hath ordained,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.14.</note> that they which preach the Goſpell, ſhould liue of the Goſpell. If God hath ordained it, firſt, it is Gods ordinance, and not mans: Secondly, if Gods ordinance, then no other ordinance then that which hee hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in his Word, which is tythes and offerings, without any mention of mans pretended compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tency.<note place="margin">1. Cor. Ibid. Mat. 23.23. Heb. 7.8.</note> Thirdly, if Gods ordinance as a morall duty, and in the time of the Goſpell, then not to be abrogated. Hath God called you to ſaluation by our Goſpell, here in my text, and to obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt by the preaching thereof? And ſhall not we obtaine at your hands thoſe temporall things which are not yours, but Gods &amp; ours, &amp; that not of almes, begging Frier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, but of right belonging vnto vs? Will Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans be worſe then the Phariſis in the performance of this duty? How then doth our righteouſnes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed the righteouſnes of the Scribes &amp; Phariſies? <hi>Quomodo abundat iuſtitia noſtra plus quàm ſcribarum &amp; Phariſaeorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen Homil. <hi>11.</hi> in Numb.</note> 
               <hi>ſi illi de fructibus terrae ſuae guſtare non audent, priuſquam primitias ſacerdotibꝰ efferant, et Leuitis de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimae ſeparentur: et ego nihil horum faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, fructibus terrae ita abutar, vt ſacerdos neſciat, Leuites ignoret, diuinum altare non
<pb facs="tcp:26209:4"/> ſentiat?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hieron. in gloſ. ſuper illud Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la. <hi>3.</hi> Omnem de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimam. &amp; Chryſoſt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per illud Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaei, Quideci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matis.</note> And heare what S. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaith to like purpoſe: <hi>Quia non reddidiſtis decimas et pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitias, idcircò in penuria et fame maledicti eſtis: quia dum parua ſubtraxiſtis, et totam abundantiam frugum et poſſeſſionum veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarum perdidiſtis, ſciatis vos ideo perdidiſſe abundantiam, quia fraudaſtis me parte me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, moneo igitur vt reddatis mihi mea, er ego reſtituam vobis veſtra.</hi> Becauſe ye haue not gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen me my tythes and firſt fruites, ye are curſed with penury and famine: becauſe that whileſt ye with held ſmall things from mee, yee loſt the whole abundance of the fruites of your poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Know yee then, that therefore ye haue loſt abundance, becauſe ye haue defrauded me of my part. Therefore I warne you that you reſtore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me thoſe things that are mine, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore thoſe things that are yours. And theſe words, <hi>The tenth is mine,</hi> ſaith the Lord,<note place="margin">Leuit. 27.30.</note> is a morall poſition, not abrogated with other ceremonies of the Law, but is ſtill in force: for as long as <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizedecks,</hi> that is, Chriſts Prieſthood, remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, which is for euer, <hi>vſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ad huius ſeculi conſummationem,</hi> to the end of the world ſo long doth the maintenance belong vnto the Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
            <p>It is againſt the rules of Logicke to write or diſpute <hi>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iis rebus de quibus non eſt du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitandum: An ignis ſit calidus?</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am ſorry that there was euer occaſion giuen by any to queſtion this truth, which is ſo apparant,
<pb facs="tcp:26209:5"/> both by authority of Scriptures,<note place="margin">Math. 23.24.</note> Fathers, and Councels: Wherein we may ſee the payment of tythes to be due to Gods Miniſters, <hi>de iure,</hi> of right; although by reaſon of the corruption of times, they were not in ſome ages paid, <hi>de facto,</hi> in deede as they ought to be. And this is the very point, if there were a thouſand volumes written on this ſubiect. What I haue ſaid briefly hereon, I returne it to Gods glory, not ſeeking mine owne praiſe; and leaue it to the Churches good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefite, not doubting, but amongst a multitude of gaine-ſaiers, ſome there will bee with wiſedome and a good conſcience, to conſider &amp; practiſe this truth. And let all men take heede, which goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to defraud God and his Miniſters of their right: That that heauy curſſe of God fall not on them and their children, which is ſpoken of by the Prophet <hi>Malachy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3.</note> To be curſſed with a curſſe for deſpoyling the Lord and his Miniſters by this ſacriledge. And on the contrary, let all ſuch (as by fearing God yeelde this obedience vnto him) to their comforts likewiſe heere learne:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibidem</hi> verſ. 10.</note> That he will open the windowes of Heauen vnto them, and powre them out a bleſsing without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And ſo with my prayers to almighty God for Sions proſperity, I reſt. <hi>This 13. of Ianuary. 1621.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in all Chriſtian loue and kindneſſe,</hi> R. I.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:26209:5"/>
            <head>The way to Glory. The Text.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2. THES. 2.14.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Whereunto he called you by our Goſpell, to obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His text is like the Oliue leafe which <hi>Noahs</hi> Doue brought in her mouth into the Arke in the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uening, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8.11. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by hee knew the Flood ceaſſed, the waters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, and that ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for himſelfe and his family approached. So is this Goſpel which our Apoſtle S. <hi>Paule</hi> brings heere as an Oliue leafe vnto the Church of <hi>Theſſalonica;</hi> it intimates ioy, and brings with it ioyfull newes, as the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> doth imply; for it is the ioyfull em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſie for the ſaluation of their ſoules. So S. <hi>Paule</hi> calls it <hi>Verbum ſalutis,</hi> The word of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:26209:6"/> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 13.26.<note place="margin">Acts 13.26.</note> 
               <hi>Vobis hoc verbum ſalutis eſt miſſum:</hi> To you is this word of ſaluation ſent, ſo it is defined by the Apoſtle, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> The power of God vnto ſaluation to euery one that doth beleeue, to the <hi>Iewe</hi> firſt, and alſo to the <hi>Greeke.</hi> It is <hi>lux magna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay 9.2.</note> that great light illuminating the darkeneſſe of our vnderſtandings: It is <hi>ſceptrum regni,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the ſcepter of the kingdome of Grace, to bring vs to the Kingdome of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Heere is <hi>Iupiters Nectar,</hi> the more it is drunke of, the more it runneth ouer: heere is water to refreſh vs, wine to cheere vs, and bread to ſtrengthen our hearts; heere is wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,<note place="margin">Iohn 4.10.</note> yea the water of Life, who ſo drinketh thereof ſhall neuer thirſt, and yet the more he drinkes the more he may.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſay 55.</hi> Rupert in Math. lib. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Omnes fitien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes venite adiaquam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: aqua eſt euangelium, in quo omnium ſpiritualium g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atiarum continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur myſteris.</hi> All yee that thirſt come to this water; this water is the Goſpell of Chriſt, in which the myſteries of all ſpirituall graces are contained.<note place="margin">Exod. 16.</note> Heere is that <hi>Manna et cibus bidu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> feeding our ſoules in this life, to that which is to come.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, heere is <hi>vera pax et tranquil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litas animi,</hi> true peace and tranquillity of the mind, wherein you may ſolace your ſelues if you pleaſe. It is S. <hi>Paule,</hi> our diuine <hi>Orphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> wiſedome, to allure vs with the ſweete me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodious ſtrings and tunes of his Goſpell: it
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:26209:6"/> ſhould bee our delight to ſolace our ſelues therein;<note place="margin">Virg. eglo <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> for here he ſings not <hi>ſylueſtrem mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam,</hi> a countrey note, but <hi>canticum diuinum,</hi> a diuine ſong or Anthem, wherein we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but take delight.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto he called you by our Goſpell, to obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Not to ſtay any longer at the entrance of my text, let vs go in and behold the beauty and glory therein contained; and which way ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer you caſt your eyes, there are moſt plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant and glorious obiects to behold. If you looke vnto the Author of our calling,<note place="margin">2. Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13.</note> he is glorious, for it is he <hi>qui ab initio elegerit vos ad ſalutem,</hi> in the precedent verſe; hee which choſe you vnto ſaluation from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; and he is <hi>Rex gloriae, Pſal.</hi> 24. the King of glory, and <hi>Deus gloriae,</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5. the God of glory, which by his Goſpell calls vs to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine his glory, and the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>If you looke vnto the calling it ſelfe, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is alſo glorious; for what more glorious then to bee called and made the ſeruant of God? <hi>Hee called you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you looke vnto the inſtrument or means <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of our calling, that is glorious alſo; for it is the Goſpell, the miniſtration of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which exceedes in glory.</p>
            <p>If you pleaſe to behold the end thereof, it is here that <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> that leades vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:26209:7"/> all glory, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>To obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Qui vocauit.</note>In this heauenly calling is firſt to bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, the Author thereof, which is God, who is alſo the Author of our election and ſanctification, in the former verſe. So that all the cauſes of our ſaluation, both prima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſecondary, both firſt and laſt, are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of and from him,<note place="margin">Reuel. 1.</note> who is ſaid to be the firſt and laſt, <hi>qui elegerit vos,</hi> he which elected you in the former verſe:<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>idem vocauit,</hi> the ſame called you, here in the text.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Vocauit vos.</note>Secondly, <hi>vocauit vos,</hi> he called you; and here wee ſee how almighty God doth euo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate and call his Elect from the reprobate, vntill which time there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene them in reſpect of nature: For vntill he called <hi>Mathew</hi> he was but a publican;<note place="margin">Mat. 9.9. Acts 9.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he called <hi>Saule,</hi> hee was but a perſecutor; vntill hee called <hi>Zachee,</hi> he was but a world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; vntill he called <hi>Peter,</hi> he was but a fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of fiſhes, and not of men, and fauoured not the things that were of God, but the things that were of men.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, in the inſtrument or meanes of our calling, which is <hi>per Euangelium noſtrum,</hi> by our Goſpell, that is <hi>per praedicationem E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelij nobis commiſsam:</hi> is to bee conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that the preaching of the Goſpell, is the ordinary meanes, which God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to call vs to ſaluation; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:26209:7"/> by our Goſpell, that is, by our preaching the Goſpell committed vnto vs, hee called you to ſaluation. And here alſo in this place may be obſerued, the dignity and neceſſity of the office of preaching the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, that it is neither ſo baſe nor ſo needleſſe an office as many account of it. For as the beſt men that euer were, and God himſelfe and his Sonne, graced this calling;<note place="margin">Geneſ. 2. Math. 9.35.</note> ſo the neceſſity thereof is ſuch, that it concernes the ſaluation of our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, <hi>in acquiſitionem gloriae,</hi> to obtaine <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, is the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod and end of all this worke: for glory ſhall be the end &amp; reward of al that obey the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Chriſt Ieſus. Where we ſee our labor is not loſt, that we ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in his ſeruice, we ſhal not goe vnrewarded for working in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard: for heere is the promiſed reward ſet downe for our encouragement, that wee ſhall obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Heere is then a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a Narration of our heauenly vocation and calling,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Part</hi> 1.</note> by the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell; in which theſe foure cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances offer themſelues to our conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Author of our calling,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cir.</hi> 1.</note> which is God, hauing reference vnto the relatiue <hi>qui,</hi> in the former verſe; he which elected you, the ſame alſo calls you, here in my text.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:26209:8"/>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. the calling it ſelf, <hi>vocauit vos,</hi> he called you.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the Inſtrument or meanes of our calling, and that is, <hi>per Euangelium noſtrum,</hi> by our Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly, the end of our calling, and that is, <hi>in acquiſitionem gloriae,</hi> to obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>And firſt of the Author of our calling, which is God, <hi>He called you.</hi> In the former verſe, and in this text, the Apoſtle ſets downe all the cauſes of our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is, Gods Election from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, <hi>quòd ab initio elegerit vos Deus ad ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutem,</hi> that God choſe you to ſaluation from <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the beginning. The ſecond is the ſanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> of the ſpirit. The Third heere in the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> text, is the preaching of the Goſpell, <hi>per Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium noſtrum, By our Goſpell.</hi> The fourth and laſt is the <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi> that leades vnto all glory, <hi>In acquiſitionem gloriae Domini noſtri Ieſu Chriſti, To obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> And all theſe come from aboue,<note place="margin">Iames 1,</note> and from the Father of lights, ſo that here we learne:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Poſito prima.</note>All the cauſes of our ſaluation both pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary and ſecondary, firſt and laſt, the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, progreſſe, and ending, are of, and from God onely. He it is onely which elected vs, which called,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note> which iuſtified, ſanctified and ſaued vs: <hi>et fidelis est qui vos vocauit, qui hoc etiam per ficiet,</hi> Faithfull is hee which called
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:26209:8"/> you, which will alſo do it:<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.24.</note> as he hath begun our ſaluation by election, ſo hee will alſo fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh the ſame by our vocation, through the preaching of the Goſpell, &amp; thereby bring vs to obtain the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Our duty therefore in this place,<note place="margin">Appli.</note> is to render the Apoſtles <hi>Debemus gratias ſemper,</hi> in the precedent verſe; Wee ought to giue thankes alwayes vnto God, for that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning he choſe vs to ſaluation, &amp; from whom alſo all the cauſes of our ſaluation do come. And with <hi>Dauid</hi> to ſing a ſong of thankſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vnto his name, <hi>O thou moſt Higheſt. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> had many ſongs in the praiſe of God, hee had his <hi>Canticum laudis,</hi> his Song of praiſe and thankſgiuing;<note place="margin">Pſal. 117.</note> 
               <hi>Praiſe the Lord all ye peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and laud him all yee Nations.</hi> And hee had his <hi>Canticum miſericordiae,</hi> his Song of Gods mercy; <hi>My Song ſhall be of the mercy and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing kindneſſe of the Lord, with my mouth will I euer be ſhewing thy praiſe, from one generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to another:</hi> And he had his <hi>Canticum grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum actionis,</hi> his Song of thankſgiuing, <hi>I will alwaies giue thankes vnto the Lord, his praiſe ſhall be euer in my mouth.</hi> And therefore I will conclude this point with the Apoſtles <hi>Cui,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.18.</note> To whom bee glory and dominion fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I come to the ſecond circumſtance, which is the calling it ſelfe, in theſe words, <hi>Vocauit vos, He called you.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:26209:9"/>
            <p>And here I neede not much ſtand to ſhew how many wayes this word <hi>Vocation</hi> and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling is taken in holy Scriptures. As ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time it is taken for an externall ciuill voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or calling; as to be called to the office or dignity of a King, to enioy the ſoueraigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note> which S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith is <hi>Officium praecellens</hi> or <hi>ſupereminens,</hi> The ſupreame Office. And this word alone layes flat in the duſt, the <hi>Popes</hi> vſurped tranſcendency ouer all, which he falſly challengeth to himſelfe. Or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it is taken for an external Eccleſiaſtical calling, as to be called to the Office &amp; digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Biſhop,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 3.1.</note> which is <hi>Opus bonum,</hi> a good worke and a weighty. Or to be called to the Office of a Magiſtrate, to puniſh wickedneſſe and vice, and to mainetaine vertue. All theſe are but externall callings, vnto which both good and bad men may be called: but yet not called inwardly, with this ſpirituall and heauenly vocation and calling:<note place="margin">1. Sam. 8 9.</note> for ſo was <hi>Saule</hi> outwardly called to be a King,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marke 14.</hi> Auguſt. lib. de gra.</note> and <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> outwardly called to be an Apoſtle, but not inwardly called with this effectuall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, which is, <hi>Doni, non meriti; gratiae, non na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae,</hi> from God and not from man, the worke of Grace and not of Nature: and this is <hi>pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus applicationis Chriſti gradus,</hi> our firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in the ſchoole of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Deſcription.</note> called by S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine ingreſſus ad ſalutem, et primus ad fidem aditus,</hi> Our entrance to ſaluation, and firſt
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:26209:9"/> approach to faith: more eſpecially, it is <hi>Actio Dei efficax et gratioſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Definitio.</note> 
               <hi>qua electi ex Dei bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placito, propter meritu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſti, per Spiritum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum, intus informantur ad preceptionem et com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munionem et gratiae et gloriae Dei:</hi> The ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, internall, effectuall vocation and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, is the gracious and effectuall worke of God, whereby his elect, of Gods good will, for the merit of Chriſt, by the operation of his Spirit, are inwardly informed for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing and participation of the grace of God; and outwardly reformed in their liues vnto good workes, for his glory. The effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe whereof, is the good will of God; the inſtrumentall cauſe twofold, internall, the operation of Gods Spirit; externall, the preaching of the Goſpell:<note place="margin">Idem.</note> 
               <hi>Vocauit vos per E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelium noſtrum,</hi> he called you by our Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, to the participation of grace in this life, and glory in the life to come.</p>
            <p>In this vocation which followes electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as yee may ſee in theſe two verſes, (for firſt God elected vs from the beginning vnto ſaluation, and then heere hee calls vs, in my Text:) we may obſerue this poſition, That <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſitio </seg>1</label> as election goeth before vocation, ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all calling alwayes followeth election, and is the manifeſtation thereof. For as the beſt way in a maine Land, to finde out the ſea,<note place="margin">Simil.</note> is to walke by the riuer that runneth into the ſea; ſo he that would finde out his election,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:26209:10"/> let him walke thereunto by his calling, as by a riuer running and flowing out of the ſea of Gods election; ſo that the beſt way to finde out our election, is by yeelding obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to this heauenly calling.<note place="margin">Theſ. 5.</note> Art thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to worke righteouſneſſe? This is a mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt token of thy election. Art thou not cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and moued (but who can ſay ſo) to work righteouſneſſe? or doeſt thou not finde a readineſſe in thy minde to obey the motions of Gods Spirit, to yeelde obedience to the Goſpell, to bee ready to euery good worke? Thou canſt no way yet aſſure thy ſelfe, that thou art of the number of Gods Elect, and to belong vnto the election of Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Applicatio.</note>For application of which place, I ſay one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> ſaid vnto the Scribes and Phariſies,<note place="margin">Mat. 3.</note> Bring forth fruites worthy of repentance, and bee not of ſuch minde to ſay, Wee haue <hi>Abraham</hi> to our father; for I ſay, that God is able of theſe ſtones to raiſe vp children vnto <hi>Abraham:</hi> God is able to break off the naturall branches throgh their diſobedience, and to graft in the wilde bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and raiſe vp dead ſtones, contrary to nature, by grace. And againe, he is of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to breake and burne the wilde branches, and to graft in againe the naturall,<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> if they continue not ſtill in their vnbeleefe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to euocate and call out from others, teacheth vs:</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:26209:10"/>
            <p>That there is no difference by nature be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſitio </seg>2</label> the Elect and the rebrobate, vntill God make it by this heauenly vocation and calling. For although <hi>Deus cognouit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.</note> be true with God, The Lord knoweth who are his, and whom he hath choſen; yet vntill he make it apparent by his effectuall calling, there is no difference betweene them and the repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, in their obedience to God.<note place="margin">Acts 9.</note> For <hi>Paul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee was called, as bold a perſecutor of the Church of God, as euer was <hi>Domitian,</hi> or <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Zache</hi> before he was called,<note place="margin">Luke. 19.2.</note> for ought appeares, as vnconſcionable a worldling, as euer was the rich glutton damned to hell: That in reſpect of the corruption of nature, there is no difference betweene the Elect and reprobate, vntill God make it by his heauenly calling. And the Apoſtles <hi>Tales fueritis</hi> in the <hi>Romans,</hi> doth ſhew it:<note place="margin">Rom, 6</note> ſuch yee were; but yee are waſhed, but ye are iuſtified, but yee are ſanctified, in the Name of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and by the Spirit of our God. Thirdly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Hee choſe and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> called you out from others, as the word doth import: &amp; this maketh the greatnes of Gods mercy appeare, that God hath taken vs from <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſitio </seg>3</label> the reprobate, &amp; brought vs to this heauenly calling. God took <hi>Lot</hi> our of <hi>Sodom</hi> that filthy place, and ſent his Angells to call him out: at firſt, not knowing the danger, hee lingred
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:26209:11"/> and was reluctant to obey their call, till at length they put hands vnto him and forced him to goe out: and beeing ſet vpon the mountaine in the plaine, when he ſaw <hi>Sodom</hi> fiered from heauen, and burning with brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, then, no doubt, hee acknowledged the wonderfull loue and mercy of God toward him.<note place="margin">Appli.</note> It is euen ſo with vs, we are ſoiourning here in <hi>Sodom,</hi> which God will deſtroy with fire, and we are among thoſe whoſe portion is in this life, but reſerued vnto the burning lake of fire and brimſtone. But God of his mercy purpoſing to ſaue vs,<note place="margin">Iudges 2.2.</note> ſent his Angells his Miniſters, not once, nor twice, but many times, calling and exhorting vs to flye from the wrath to come. And thus much for <hi>Vo cauit vos, Hee called you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Cir.</note>I come vnto the third circumſtance, which is the inſtrument or meanes of our calling, <hi>per Euangelium noſtrum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Per Euangelium</note> 
               <hi>by our Goſpell,</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he called you by our Goſpell. Why is it called here our Goſpell? Is it not the Goſpell of God and of Chriſt? Yes verily, both as it ſprung from him, and as hee is the author of it.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.2.</note> So S. <hi>Paule</hi> calls it the Goſpell of God: <hi>We were bold to ſpeak vnto you the Goſpel of God,</hi> and S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſo calls it alſo,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17.</note> 
               <hi>What ſhal be the end of thoſe that obey not the Goſpell of God?</hi> And it is properly called alſo the Goſpell of Chriſt.<note place="margin">Mar. 1.1.</note> For ſo the Euangeliſts ſtile it:<note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> &amp; the Apoſtle S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſo calls it; <hi>I am not aſhamed of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:26209:11"/> Goſpell of Chriſt:</hi> and againe,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians; Onely let your conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be as it becommeth the Goſpell of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> How is it then called <hi>our Goſpell, Paules</hi> goſpell, and <hi>Peters</hi> goſpell, and <hi>Iohns</hi> goſpell, and our goſpell? For ſo it is called here, <hi>Hee called you by our Goſpell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo in the <hi>Corinths</hi> it is called our goſpell; <hi>If our Goſpell be hid,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>it is hid to them that are loſt.</hi> Nay, ſometimes it is more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially called my goſpell;<note place="margin">Rom. 2.16.</note> as in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Romans; At that day when God ſhall iudge the ſecrets of men by Ieſus Chriſt, according to my Goſpell:</hi> and againe in the ſame Epiſtle; <hi>To him now that is of power to ſtabliſh you accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to my Goſpell, and preaching of Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 16.25.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> How then is it Gods goſpell, and <hi>Paules</hi> goſpell, and our Goſpell? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Aretius</hi> on this Text anſwers well to this queſtion: Saith he, <hi>Dei eſt, et Pauli eſt Euangelium; Dei eſt, tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Authoris; Pauli eſt Euangelium, vt eius ei commiſsa eſt praedicatio.</hi> It is Gods goſpell and <hi>Paules</hi> goſpell: It is Gods goſpell, as hee is the author of it, and as it ſprung from him; it is <hi>Paules</hi> goſpell, as the preaching thereof is committed vnto him.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe ſaith <hi>Marlorat</hi> on this Text; <hi>Apoſtolus Euangelium appellat ſuum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marlorat</hi> on the Text.</note> 
               <hi>non quaſi apud ſe natum, ſed cuius illi praedicatio mandata fuerat.</hi> The Apoſtle calls the goſpell his goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, not that it ſprung from him, or that he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:26209:12"/> was the author of it, but as the preaching thereof was commanded him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Senſe.</note>The meaning of theſe words, hee called you, <hi>per Euangelium noſtrum,</hi> by our Goſpell, is, <hi>per praedicationem Euangelij nobis commiſſam,</hi> by our preaching the goſpell which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted vnto vs. It is then Chriſts goſpell properly, and it is our goſpell as the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching thereof is committed and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vs. So then in reſpect of preaching the goſpell, it is S. <hi>Paules</hi> goſpell, it is S. <hi>Peters</hi> goſpell, it is S. <hi>Iohns</hi> goſpell, and it is the goſpell of euery faithfull miniſter of Chriſt, as the preaching and diſpenſation thereof is committed vnto him: For God gaue in the Apoſtles a commiſſion to all his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters their ſucceſſors,<note place="margin">Their commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from God. Mat. 28.19. Marke 16.15.</note> 
               <hi>Ite in mundum,</hi> goe into all the world, and preach the goſpell: hee that beleeueth and is baptized, ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; he that will not beleeue ſhall bee dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. So that they hauing a commiſſion from God, to preach the goſpell, it is ſaid to bee theirs in reſpect of the preaching thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>2</label> Heere then another queſtion may ariſe, what difference there is betweene the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles goſpell, that is, the Text of the goſpell; and our goſpell, that is, the preaching, diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, expoſition, gloſſe, or determination thereof? <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwer. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, there is an imparity and difference betweene the Text of the Goſpell, in which there can be no error or lye, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:26209:12"/> our expoſition and gloſſe thereof, in which there may be errors: as we haue ſeene in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the famous and worthy Fathers,<note place="margin">Aug. de ciuitat. lib. <hi>21.</hi> Idem de doctr. Chriſtian.</note> and Pillars of the Church. Firſt, the Text of the goſpell cannot erre nor lye; ſo ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Vnder the hope of eternal life, which <hi>God</hi> that cannot lye,<note place="margin">Tit. 1.2.</note> hath promiſed before the world beganne. And againe, We cannot but ſpeake the truth of thoſe things we haue ſeen and heard. And againe,<note place="margin">Acts 4.20.</note> We can do nothing againſt the truth, but for the truth.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.8.</note> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, in the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> Though that we or an Angell from heauen,<note place="margin">Gal 1.8.</note> preach vnto you otherwiſe then that which we haue preached, let him be accurſed. And here S. <hi>Paule</hi> doth pronounce the Pope,<note place="margin">If his traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and lawes be againſt Gods word.</note> 
               <hi>Peters</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor (if the Papiſts will haue him ſo) accur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, if he teach or preach otherwiſe, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to S. <hi>Paules</hi> Doctrine; and that he doth ſo, who ſeeth not that hath eyes? Moſt of his Doctrines, Pardons, Indulgences, Acts, Excommunications, and Lawes, beeing flat againſt the Doctrine of S. <hi>Paule,</hi> and the truth of Gods word, as I ſhal hereafter touch. But here we ſee that there is, and may bee a great difference and imparity betweene the Text of the goſpel and our preaching there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: For ſo ſaith alſo S. <hi>Auguſtine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de videndo Deo ad Pauli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, cap. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Numquid vllo modo Euangelio ſcripta mea comparabis, aut ea Scripturis canonicis coaequabis? Profectò ſi rectè diiudicando ſapis, longè infra nos vides ab
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:26209:13"/> illa authoritate diſtare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Trel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. Qua au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate egeat ſcriptura, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>geat non propter ſe ſed propter alia.</hi> The Church deliuereth the truth, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth not the ſame:</p>
                  <p>That muſt bee done by ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. Scripture is beſt expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Tit. 1.2. The Diuels reſtauration. <hi>Aug. de ciui. lib.</hi> 21. 2 Beginning.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>et me quidem longiùs.</hi> Doeſt any way compare my writings with the goſpell, or equalize them with the Text of the Canonicall Scriptures? Truely, if thou vnderſtandeſt with a right iudgement, thou maiſt perceiue vs and our writings much inferiour to their authority, and my ſelfe moſt inferiour of all.</p>
            <p>Now heere we ſee the text of Gods goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell and word cannot lye, there is no error in it. But in the writings and bookes of men of ſubordinate calling, there may bee error, as was in <hi>Origen, Auguſtine,</hi> and many of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church; why may it not bee in the Pope alſo, and his expoſitions and gloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Scripture? which our aduerſaries deny: for they hold and maintaine this doctrine: That the Popes defining and expounding Scriptures <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Poſito Papiſtica</note> is to be beleeued as the vndoubted truth, and held for the moſt certaine rule and ground of faith; and equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize his expoſitions, and traditions, with the goſpell.<note place="margin">Baron Tom. <hi>1.</hi> in Annal. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> So ſaith <hi>Baronius:</hi> By the tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Church all the goſpell recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth his authority, and is built thereupon as vpon a foundation, and cannot ſubſiſt without it.<note place="margin">Tom. <hi>2.</hi> de ſign. eccleſ pag. <hi>133.</hi>
               </note> Likewiſe ſaith <hi>Bozius,</hi> The Scriptures are not to bee reckoned among ſuch principle as before all things are to bee credited:<note place="margin">Blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</note> But they are proued and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Church, as by a certaine princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:26209:13"/> which hath authority to reiect and allow Scripture. Here is flat hereſie and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my againſt the truth of Scriptures; equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing, nay preferring their writings and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority before the Scriptures.<note place="margin">Stapleton Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinicat. aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Whitak.</note> Yet <hi>Stapleton</hi> one of their owne ſide, of a milder ſpirit, is cleane of contrary opinion: For hee ſaith, The inward teſtimony of the Spirit, is ſo ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall, that by it alone, any matter may be beleeued, though the Church holde her peace.</p>
            <p>Heere wee ſee our aduerſaries errors and contradictions about this point; they equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lize and preferre their writings with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: they will beleeue no Scripture,<note place="margin">No Scripture ought to bee expounded a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſis</hi> &amp; ground of Faith.</note> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe their Church expound it; and though their Church expound the ſame neuer ſo contradictory to the truth of Scriptures, yet they then wil beleeue it, and not before. And that place which they vrge out of S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> for their purpoſe heerein, is alſo flat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelues;<note place="margin">Aug. Tome <hi>6.</hi> lib. contra epiſt. Fundamenti, cap. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ego verò non crederem E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangelio, niſi me catholicae Eccleſiae commoueret authoritas:</hi> I my ſelfe ſhould not haue beene a Chriſtian and beleeued the Goſpell, if the authority of the catholike Church had not moued and preſſed mee thereunto. Theſe words are <hi>Auguſtines</hi> text indeede, in his ſixt <hi>Tome,</hi> in his Book <hi>Contra Epiſtolam Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti, cap.</hi> 5. for that ſixt <hi>Tome,</hi> he hath written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt diuers hereſies of the <hi>Iewes, Manichies,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:26209:14"/> Arians</hi> and <hi>Iouinians.</hi> And this booke hee writes againſt the afore-named <hi>Fundaments</hi> Epiſtle which was a <hi>Manichie,</hi> and held two natures or beginnings, one good, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bad or euill; and ſaies theſe words to this intent, to conuince him of his error, by the authority and conſent of the catholike Church, which hath power to compell a Chriſtian to beleeue in Chriſt: for ſaith S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> to him, Doeſt thou not beleeue the catholike Churches whole conſent? Why I my ſelfe had not beene a Chriſtian, vnleſſe the authority and generall conſent of the Church had mooued me thereunto; putting according to phraſe the preterim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectence for the preterpluperfectence: meaning, I had not my ſelfe beene a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, vnleſſe the Churches authority, that is, generall conſent, at the firſt had preſſed me to beleeue the Goſpell: for this is apparent in his words following; <hi>Quibus ego obtempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem dicentibus Credite Euangelio;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Idem.</note> 
               <hi>cur non eis ob temperem dicentibus mihi, Noli credere Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeo? elige quid vis; ſi dixeris crede catholicis, ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi me mouent vt nullam fidem accommodem vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis.</hi> Whom I haue obeyed, ſaying, Beleeue the Goſpell, why ſhould I not alſo obey them ſaying, Beleeue not a <hi>Manachie?</hi> chuſe what thou wilt: If thou ſaiſt vnto me, Be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leeue the orthodox catholikes; they ſhall moue me ſo farre, as that I ſhould neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:26209:14"/> the <hi>Manichies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The conſent of an orthodox Church ought to conuince one and to make him a Chriſtian to beleeue the Goſpell. S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeakes of the Catholike Church, not of the Roman. The Church of Rome and her Doctrine dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fereth much from what it did in former time. The Church of Rome was ſubordinate to other Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes. <hi>Carion Cron.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>That which may be gathered from thence, is this, That the conſent of the orthodox Church hath power and authority to preſſe one to beleeue the Goſpell, and to be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: wee grant it, but not to beleeue euery poſition and doctrine, that a Church main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, eſpecially againſt the truth of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>Secondly, at that time there were no ſuch errors and ſuperſtitions in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> as now there are.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he that is read in ſtories knowes well, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> then had not the primacy of all other Churches. For the <hi>Patriarkes</hi> of <hi>Antioch, Alexandria,</hi> and <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> did challenge a parity at leaſt, with the <hi>Patriarke</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> before <hi>Phocas</hi> a murderer gaue it vnto him.</p>
            <p>Therefore I conclude this point, if any Church, or any Angell from heauen,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.</note> ſhould teach and maintaine doctrine contrary to Scripture and the truth thereof, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the <hi>Analyſis,</hi> and grounds of Faith, we ought not to beleeue him, or to ground vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his doctrine. But if you will compare S. <hi>Paules</hi> or S. <hi>Peters</hi> Doctrine (whoſe ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor they affirme the <hi>Pope</hi> to bee,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on muſt bee in Doctrine, not in perſon or place.</note>) you ſhall ſurely ſee not a ſucceſſion in doctrine, if in place. Nay if you will examine the Goſpell of S. <hi>Peter</hi> or S. <hi>Paule,</hi> with the Goſpell and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:26209:15"/> doctrine that now the church of <hi>Rome</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth, he that hath but a ſparke of indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent iudgement may ſee, that there is a won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull difference betweene them:<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.13.</note> For S. <hi>Peters</hi> Goſpell ſaith, the Kings office is the ſupreame office, the Popes Goſpell ſaith no: That all Kings are ſubordinate to him. He hath alſo temporall authority, for hee challengeth not onely to excommunicate them, but to depoſe them, and diſpoſe of their Kingdomes as he pleaſeth: as we ſee it came to paſſe by the lamentable experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of many Emperours, and of <hi>Henry</hi> the 4. of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> who being firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated by <hi>Pope Gregory</hi> the 7. called <hi>Hildebrand,</hi> his Kingdome was alſo by him giuen away to <hi>Ralphe</hi> Duke of <hi>Sweathland</hi> with this golden inſcription,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Carion.</hi> 4. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.</note> 
               <hi>Petra dedit Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tro, Petrus Diadema Rodolpho:</hi> The Rock gaue to <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> gaue the Diademe and ſoueraignty of the Empire of <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Ralphe</hi> Duke of <hi>Sweathland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And who knoweth not, that <hi>Zachary</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> did depoſe <hi>Childerich</hi> the right full King of <hi>France,</hi> and place <hi>Pipine</hi> his trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous vſurping ſeruant in his ſtead?<note place="margin">Plat. in vita A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian. et Leo. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> And <hi>Pope Adrian</hi> afterward went about to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Empire from the <hi>Greekes</hi> to the <hi>French</hi> in the perſon of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, who was but the ſonne of the afore-named <hi>Pipine</hi> the vſurper. And <hi>Pope Leo</hi> the third
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:26209:15"/> eſtabliſhed him, and therein gaue him the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pope Alexander</hi> excommunicated <hi>Frederick Barbaroſſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cario.</hi> 4. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch.</note> &amp; when he humbled himſelf to the Biſhop, hee impriſoned him in his houſe, and trode vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, &amp; cauſed his Friers to ſing, <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per aſpidem et baſiliſcum ambulabis, &amp;c.</hi> Thou ſhalt go vpon the Lyon and the Dragon, the young Lyon ſhalt thou tread vnder thy feet, &amp;c. <hi>O horrendam regi indignitatem!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay of the murders of the <hi>Henries</hi> of <hi>France,</hi>
               <note place="margin">French Chro.</note> of the famous houſes of <hi>Valois</hi> and <hi>Burbon?</hi> who were traiterouſly murdered by the practice of the <hi>Iacobines</hi> and <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> the <hi>Popes</hi> Goſpellers? And who is ignorant of the manifold treaſons that were complotted by theſe Goſpellers, againſt the late Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> of famous memory?<note place="margin">Doctor <hi>Abbots</hi> anſwer to <hi>Hils</hi> reaſons.</note> The excommunications againſt her by <hi>Pope Pius</hi> the 5. the declaration of the ſame made manifeſt by <hi>Sixtus</hi> the 5. the ſame ratified by <hi>Clement</hi> the 8. The manifold treaſons inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt her by <hi>Parry, Lopaz, Squier, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bington,</hi> and others: The aiding of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible Nauy in 1588. all which traiterous deſignes were warranted by the goſpell of the <hi>Pope,</hi> his Prieſts and <hi>Ieſuites.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gods word and Goſpell ſaith,<note place="margin">Pſal. 105</note> 
               <hi>Touch not mine Annoynted, and doe my Prophets no harme.</hi> The <hi>Ieſuites</hi> goſpell is, Touch them, curſe them, depoſe them, diſpoſe of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:26209:16"/> ſtab them, murder them, blow them vp with gunpouder, and what not? And this is their goſpell, which they teach, and which they put in practice; which things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing moſt apparently knowne to be as true as goſpell,<note place="margin">Ieſuits Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme.</note> it were to be wiſhed that al chriſtian Princes would take heed and beware of ſuch goſpellers (if ſuch there bee found) amongſt them,<note place="margin">4. Kings 10.25.</note> to reward the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as <hi>Iehu</hi> did <hi>Baals</hi> prieſts, to let none eſcape that is found: or to doe vnto them as <hi>Samuel</hi> did,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.33.</note> hew theſe traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Agags</hi> in pieces before the Lord.</p>
            <p>But leauing theſe goſpellers to their goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,<note place="margin">Text.</note> let vs returne to the Goſpell of our A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle S. <hi>Paule, Whereunto he called you by our Goſpell, to obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſitio </seg>1</label> Chriſt.</hi> And here firſt we learne, That the preaching of the Goſpell is the ſecondary meanes that God hath appointed to bring vs vnto ſaluation. For whereunto hee called you by our goſpell, that is, by our preaching the goſpell: and therefore it is called <hi>Poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia Dei ad ſalutem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.16.</note> The power of God vnto ſaluation, vnto them that beleeue, and obey the ſame.<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.</note> It is <hi>Lucerna pedibus,</hi> a Lanterne vnto our feete, and a light vnto our pathes, to leade vs from ignorance and impiety, to true vnderſtanding and godlineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Poſitio </seg>2</label> Secondly, ſeeing we are called to obtaine the glory of Chriſt by our goſpell, that is, by the preaching the goſpell: wee may heere
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:26209:16"/> learne the dignity and neceſſity of this office of preaching the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>It is not ſuch a meane and baſe office as many account of, for the beſt men that euer were haue in their owne perſons graced this calling: for <hi>Dauid</hi> is as often ſtiled <hi>Dauid</hi> the prophet, as <hi>Dauid</hi> the King, and <hi>Salomon</hi> ſtiled himſelfe The preacher.<note place="margin">Eccleſt. 1.</note> And almighty God himſelfe was the firſt preacher that euer was in the world,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> for hee preached both the law and the goſpell, to our parents in paradiſe: and our Sauiour though he were euery way a rightfull King, being heire of all things, yet tooke vpon him the office of preaching: Ieſus went about all Cities and Townes, teaching in their Synagogues,<note place="margin">Mat. 9.35.</note> and preaching the goſpell of the Kingdome, and healing euery ſickneſſe, and euery diſeaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the people. And the very titles that the holy Ghoſt doth giue them in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſhewes both the dignity and neceſſity of their office: as they are called Seers, Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, Chariots of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Planters, Waterers, Builders, Stewards, Watchmen, Souldiers, Nurſes, the Seruants of the high God,<note place="margin">Acts 2. Cor. 6.</note> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers together with God, Fathers, Elders, Men of God, friends of God, diſpenſers of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets of God, Prophets, Angels,<note place="margin">Iudges 2.2.</note> titles of great dignity and honour.</p>
            <p>Their office then is not <hi>inuentum huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> an inuention of man,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.28.</note> but <hi>Inſtitutum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinum,</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:26209:17"/> an Ordinance of God; for they are appointed of God, to be <hi>Patres nutritij,</hi> nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Fathers, feeding vs with the ſincere milke of the word of God,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.2.</note> that thereby wee may grow vp to ſaluation: and to be ſhort, that thereby we may at laſt obtaine the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Appli. 1.</note>Seeing then that the preaching of the Goſpell is the ordinary meanes that God hath appointed to call vs vnto ſaluation, and ſince alſo ſuch is the dignity and neceſſity of the office of preaching the Goſpell, that it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cernes our ſaluation; let al true Chriſtians here learne, to giue them their rights &amp; dues that belong vnto ſuch men of ſo high an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and calling, both in their dignity and maintenance: For their dignity the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſaith, <hi>Videte,</hi> See that you haue them in ſingular reuerence for their workes ſake, and be at peace with them. <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> was reueren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by <hi>Alexander</hi> as his father, becauſe that from his father he had but life, but from his maiſter he had knowledge how to liue.</p>
            <p>And truly, if, Feare the Lord, and honour his Miniſters, be married together, then cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainely they which diſhonour the ſeruants of the liuing God,<note place="margin">Eccle. 7.</note> there is but little loue to their maiſter, and little feare of God before their eyes.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Sic aeſtimet nos,</hi> Let a man ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme vs as the Miniſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the ſecrets of God. Howbeit,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:26209:17"/> ſuch is the iniquity of our times, that as the ſhaddow went backe ten degrees in the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of <hi>Ahaz,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 10.11.</note> ſo ten degrees do the ſhaddowes of Chriſt (his Miniſters I meane) goe backe in their eſteeme in the world: and as they goe ten degrees backe in their eſteeme, ſo they goe 20. degrees backe in their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, for the moſt part of them. And that maintenance which almighty God hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned theſe his ſeruants in his word for their wages, is now in this criticke age called in queſtion, whether God aſſigned it or no in his word; as if God would command his ſeruants in his word the great worke of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, and not in the ſame word allow them alſo wages for their worke: or leaue it to the courteſie or diſcretion of men, to determine by humane lawes a competent maintenance, as they terme it, for them.</p>
            <p>As touching therefore the ſeuerall and contradictory opinions about this queſtion in this age, <hi>An Decimae ſint iure diuino:</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tithes bee due by the word of God or not? This being within the compaſſe of my Text, I cannot ſuſpend my iudgement, but I will briefly determine it. And I confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and vnfeignedly hold and beleeue affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiuely againſt all refractory and ſchiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall ſpirits oppoſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> this truth:<note place="margin">Poſitio.</note> That tithes are due, <hi>iure diuino,</hi> by the diuine and morall law of God, and that they ought to
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:26209:18"/> be paid, <hi>de iure,</hi> of right, although through the corruption of the times, they haue not beene paid, <hi>de facto,</hi> as they ought to be. And this I will prooue by Scriptures, Fathers, Councels, and Arguments; and laſtly, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the obiections againſt this truth. Firſt let vs looke on theſe places of Scripture:<note place="margin">Gen. 14.20.</note> 
               <hi>Abraham (and Leuy in Abraham) paid Tythes to Melchizedeck: The Prieſt-hood remaineth for euer,</hi> ergo <hi>the maintenance belongeth to that Prieſt-hood for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 28.22.</note>
               <hi>Iacob</hi> built an houſe vnto God, and gaue vnto him the tenth of all he had: <hi>And this ſtone which I haue ſet vp ſhall be Gods houſe, and of all that thou ſhalt giue mee, I will giue the tenth vnto thee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 27.30.</note> 
               <hi>Alſo all the tythe of the land, both of the ſeede and of the ground, and of the fruite of the trees, is the Lords, it is holy to the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> If men ſay, this is a Leuiticall ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall law, and therefore abrogated:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, This, with diuers other the like in the book of <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> are morall poſitions, and are not abrogated.</p>
            <p>As in <hi>Leuiticus</hi> 17.7. They muſt not offer offerings vnto deuills, for that man ſhall bee cut off from his people, is a morall poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And <hi>Leuiticus</hi> 18. How marriages are lawfull, and not, are morall precepts. And againe, Yee ſhall not ſteale, nor deale falſly,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:26209:18"/> neither lye one to another.<note place="margin">Leuit. 19.11.12</note> Alſo yee ſhall not ſweare by my Name falſly, neither ſhalt thou defile the Name of God, I am the Lord.</p>
            <p>Theſe are morall poſitions in <hi>Leuiticus,</hi> Thou ſhalt not ſweare falſly, thou ſhalt not ſteale, &amp;c. and therefore not abrogated. So is alſo this law of paying tythes a morall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as I will hereafter ſhew, and therefore not abrogated.</p>
            <p>For breuities ſake I will onely quote pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for the proofe of this truth.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Numb.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Deut.</hi> 14.22. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 10.37. <hi>Malachie</hi> 3.8. <hi>Math.</hi> 23.23. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.12. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.13. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.8. All which places are moſt pregnant proofes that tythes are due, <hi>iure diuino,</hi> by Gods morall law; and the obiections which the aduerſe patt can extract out of theſe places to contradict this truth, are vaine and triuiall. But aboue all in my iudgement, theſe two places in Scripture are very pertinent to the purpoſe we haue now in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yee tythe mint and anniſe and commin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 23.23.</note> 
               <hi>and leaue the weightier matters of the Law, as iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, mercy, and truth. Theſe ought yee to haue done, and not to haue left the other vndone.</hi> Here our Sauiour vpbraides the Phariſies for doing the leaſt moral duties, and neglecting the weightieſt. But yet he concludes,<note place="margin">Origen homil. <hi>11.</hi> in Numb.</note> that they are all morall duties, for they ought all
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:26209:19"/> to be done. Paying of tithes is heere recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a morall duty, and with the morall duties of iudgement, mercy, and truth, which ought both in the time of the Law and the Goſpell to haue beene done. <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>
               </label> If any obiect, that in this place tythes ought to haue bene paid in the time of the Law, and that Chriſt here ſpake of what ought to haue bene done in the time of the Law, and not in the time of the Goſpell:</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> I anſwer, that what is a morall duty, and ought to haue beene done in the time of the Law, ought alſo to bee done in time of the Goſpell.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>2</label> Secondly, tything, mercy, iuſtice, and truth, are heere reckoned all for morall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, becauſe they ought all to haue beene done. But morall duties ought to bee done in the time of the Goſpell, as well as in the time of the Law:<note place="margin">Origen ibid.</note> 
               <hi>ergo</hi> paying of tythes, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy, being morall duties, ought to be done in the time of the Goſpell, as well as in the time of the Law: and this word <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portet</hi> ought or muſt, implies, that they are all morall duties. Againe, in <hi>Hebrewes</hi> 7.8. <hi>Here men that dye receiue tithes, but there hee receiueth them of whom it is witneſſed that hee liueth; and to ſay as the thing is,</hi> Leuy <hi>alſo which receiued tythes, paied tythes in</hi> Abraham.</p>
            <p>Here firſt we ſee, that tythes ought to be paid vnto Chriſts Miniſters, as they haue a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:26209:19"/> leaſe of them from him; during their mortall liues: But the inheritance of tythes belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to <hi>Melchiſedecks,</hi> that is, to Chriſts Prieſt-hood, which liueth a Prieſt for euer; and vnto whom they are rightfully and true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly due, and ought to bee paid ſo long as his Prieſt-hood remaines, which is, <hi>Ad huius ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culi conſummationem,</hi> to the end of the world; ſo long doth the maintenance belong there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto: and this is not a temporary leuiticall right, as due onely in <hi>Leuies</hi> time (for hee had but the aſſignation and leaſe of tythes but during his prieſt-hood) but a perpetual duty done before <hi>Leuies</hi> time: for <hi>Leuy,</hi> ſaith the text, paid tythes in <hi>Abraham;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb 7.9.</note> and muſt bee done alſo after <hi>Leuies</hi> time, to <hi>Melchiſedecks,</hi> that is, to Chriſts perpetuall prieſt-hood for euer.</p>
            <p>As touching the opinion of the Fathers for paying tythes,<note place="margin">2 The Fathers opinion of Tythes.</note> I will onely cite two or three places for breuities ſake. <hi>Origen</hi> in his 11. homily vpon <hi>Numb.</hi> hath theſe words, <hi>Quomodo abundat Iuſtitia noſtra plus quam Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barum et Phariſaeorum, ſi illi de fructibus terrae ſuae guſtare non audent priuſquam primitias ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotibus efferant, et Leuitis decimae ſeparen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur: et ego nihil horum faciens, fructibus terrae ita abutar, vt Sacerdos neſciat, Leuites ignoret, diuinum altare non ſentiat?</hi> How doth our righteouſneſſe abound more then the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſies, if
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26209:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:26209:20"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:26209:21"/> they durſt not once taſte of the fruites of the earth, before they had paid tythes thereof to their Prieſts, and the tenth ſeparated to the Leuites: &amp; I doing none of theſe, do ſo abuſe the fruites of the earth, that neither the Prieſt, nor Leuite, nor the diuine altar hath any taſte or feeling thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Cypri. in epiſt. <hi>66</hi>
               </note>The presbyters haue nothing to doe with ſecular affaires, but as the Leuites which had nothing to doe but to attend on the altar: ſo hath the Lord prouided for Miniſters, that they might not bee drawne by worldly occaſions from their holy buſineſſe, but might liue of that honourable ſtipend with their bretheren, as they who receiued tythes of the fruite of the earth. Here is no new coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned competence mentioned: but that hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſtipend due to <hi>Leuies</hi> ſucceſſors.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Aug. in Math. cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Haec eſt Domini iuſtiſſima conſuetudo, vt ſi tu illi decimam non dederis, tu ad decimam reuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beris, id eſt, Daemonibus, quae eſt decima Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum, aſſociaberis, dabis inquit impio militi, quod non vis dare ſacerdoti.</hi> This is the iuſt cuſtome of God, that if thou wilt not giue him his tenth, thou ſhalt bee brought backe to thy tenth, and ſhalt be ioyned with deuils, which is the tenth part of Angels &amp;c. <hi>Si de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimam dederis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ibid.</note> 
               <hi>non ſolum abundantia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fructuum accipies, ſed etiam ſanitatem animae et corporis conſequeris &amp;c.</hi> If thou paiſt tythes, thou ſhalt not onely receiue abundance of fruites of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26209:21"/> earth, but the ſweete fruite alſo of the ſoule and body. S. <hi>Ierome</hi> alſo hath theſe words.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Quia non dediſtis decimas et primitias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hier. in gloſ. ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per illud, Mal. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>id<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circo in penuria et fame maledicti eſtis: quia dum parua ſubtraxiſtis, et totam abundantiam frugum et poſſeſſionum veſtrarum perdidiſtis: ſciatis vos ideo perdidiſſe abundantiam, quia fraudauiſtis me parte mea; moneo igitur, vt red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datis mihi mea, et ego reſtituam vobis veſtra.</hi> Becauſe yee haue not giuen vnto mee my tenths and firſt fruites, yee are curſed with penury and famine; becauſe that whileſt you with-held ſmall things from me, yee loſt the whole abundance of the fruites of your poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions. Know yee then, that therefore yee haue loſt abundance, becauſe ye haue defrau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me of my part: Therefore I warne you that you reſtore vnto mee thoſe things that are mine, and I will reſtore vnto you thoſe things that are yours.</p>
            <p>Infinite places moe I might rehearſe to this purpoſe, but for breuities ſake I will onely quote them.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Auguſtine in ſermo. de decimis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Inferte omnem decimam.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſt. ſuper illud Mathaei, cap.</hi> 23. <hi>Qui decimatis, &amp;c. Hiero. in Malachiam</hi> 3. <hi>Inferte omnem decimam, &amp;c. et reuertimini, &amp;c. Chryſoſt. ibidem, Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtom homil.</hi> 3. <hi>aduerſus Iudaeos; idem homil.</hi> 4. <hi>de verbis Iſayae. Idem ſuper Math. Idem hom.</hi> 8. <hi>imperf. Operis. Idem homil.</hi> 34. <hi>homil.</hi> 38. <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil.</hi> 43. <hi>Operis imperfecti:</hi> with many moe
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:26209:22"/> places to like purpoſe. And as concerning Councells,<note place="margin">Decrees and Councells.</note> I will onely but quote them for breuities ſake in the margent: for after the diuiſions of pariſhes which was by <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Biſhop of Rome,<note place="margin">Decreta Dionyſ. &amp; cauſ. <hi>13.</hi> q. <hi>14</hi> Dionyſ. cauſ. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>2.</hi> Plat. in vita Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onyſii. Polydor. Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil. lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Decret. Dionyſi. cauſ. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> about the yeare 266. were tythes aſſigned to their ſeuerall baptiſmall and pariſh Churches, that none might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trude vpon each other; which was long be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Councell of <hi>Lateran.</hi> And therefore it is an error which ſome hold, that tythes were not due nor aſſigned to pariſh Churches before the Councell of <hi>Lateran:</hi> for <hi>Dionyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Cauſ.</hi> 3. <hi>q.</hi> 2. <hi>Singulas Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias pro ſuis miniſtris aſſignauimus, &amp;c.</hi> Wee haue aſſigned ſeuerall Churches for ſeuerall Miniſters,<note place="margin">Leo. <hi>4.</hi> de deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis. Concil. Toled. cauſ. <hi>16. 1.</hi> Idem, Quicunq voluerit.</note> and diuided to each their pariſhes and Church-yards, and appointed that eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſhould haue their proper right, ſo that none may intrude vpon the pariſh of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>So ſaith <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> in his <hi>Canon, Statuimus, &amp;c.</hi> To the like purpoſe ſaith the Councell of <hi>Wor. q.</hi> 7. <hi>Et Marcellus Patauinus, Defenſ. Pac.</hi> part 2. <hi>Can.</hi> 14. <hi>Conc. Toled. ſeſ.</hi> 4. <hi>Can.</hi> 32. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium Matiſconenſe. ſeſ</hi> 2. <hi>Can.</hi> 6. <hi>et cauſ.</hi> 16. <hi>q.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Thus we ſee tythes to be due, <hi>iure diuino,</hi> by diuine right, by Scriptures, Fathers, and Councels. Now 3. or 4. arguments for proofe thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that tythes are due <hi>iure diuino.</hi>
               </note>Firſt, it is granted by all men, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:26209:22"/> muſt haue by Gods Word ſufficient maintenance, and wages for their worke, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 9.13. and other places.</p>
            <p>If by Gods Word Miniſters muſt haue <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>1</label> maintenance, then either more then the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uites</hi> had, or leſſe then the <hi>Leuites</hi> had, or the ſame which they had aſſigned vnto them by almighty God.</p>
            <p>But Miniſters muſt haue maintenance by Gods Word,<note place="margin">Math. 23.23. 1. Cor. 9.7. 1. Cor. 9.13.</note> 
               <hi>ergo</hi> either more then the <hi>Leuites</hi> had, or leſſe, or the ſame.</p>
            <p>Now more then the <hi>Leuites</hi> had, the world will not allow them, neither doe the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters require it, but are content with that portion that God aſſigned to their brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren.</p>
            <p>And to giue them leſſe then the <hi>Leuites</hi> had, is to vnder-value their Miniſtery, and to make it inferiour to the <hi>Leuites</hi> Moſaicall Miniſtery; and to preferre the miniſtration of condemnation, before the miniſtration of righteouſneſſe, which doth exceede in glory. Therefore if their maintenance bee not more nor leſſe then <hi>Leuies,</hi> it muſt bee the ſame, which is the tenth.</p>
            <p>Againe, that which God commanded <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>2</label> in his Word, and was practiſed by many ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, and was neuer abrogated by God, is ſtill in force: But God commanded in his Word tythes to be paid: many godly men practiſed the ſame, and the ordinance was
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:26209:23"/> neuer abrogated: <hi>Ergo</hi> the duty of paying tythes is ſtill in force. That God commands this duty, that fearefull execration of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God,<note place="margin">Deut. 14.22. Mal. 3.8. Nehe. 10.37. Math. 23.23. Gen. 14.20. &amp; 28.22.</note> by the mouth of his Prophet <hi>Malachie,</hi> in his third chapter, ſheweth hee commands them to bring his tythes into his houſe, and hee commands them with a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; for he ſubioynes a fearefull penalty, a curſe vpon the heads of thoſe that neglect this duty: and this he neuer abrogated, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame is ſtill in force.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>3</label> Againe, that which is the Lords inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance properly, and the property and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite thereof aſſigned to his Miniſters,<note place="margin">Leuit. 27.30. &amp; the places a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue cited. Leuit. 27.30.</note> no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man ought to vſurpe and take from them, but muſt be due vnto them. But tythes are the Lords, the benefit and vſe of them he hath aſſigned to his Miniſters, <hi>Ergo,</hi> no man ought to vſurpe or take it from them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 27.30.</note>The Tenth is mine, ſaith the Lord; and this hee hath aſſigned to his Miniſters, <hi>Ergo</hi> it is their dues to haue it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>4</label>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.7. &amp; 9.13.</note>The Miniſters muſt haue their wages and maintenance, either of right or of Almes; not of Almes, for that were too beggerly and baſe for ſo high and holy a calling: <hi>Ergo</hi> they muſt haue their maintenance of right, and of that kinde which is aſſigned in his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Word.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>5</label>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.17.7.8.9. &amp; 8.9.</note>Tythes properly belong to Chriſts prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood: The prieſthood remaines for euer: <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:26209:23"/> the maintenance due to that prieſthood muſt remaine for euer.</p>
            <p>The paying of tythes is no ceremoniall <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Argu. </seg>6</label> nor iudiciall, <hi>Ergo</hi> a morall duty.</p>
            <p>No ceremoniall duty, for they were paid before <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſince the ceremoniall law; <hi>Ergo</hi> no ceremoniall duty: becauſe a ceremony is but a type of an holy thing to come; and it is for a time.<note place="margin">Leuit. 27.30.31</note> Tythes are holy things themſelues, and holy to the Lord, <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go</hi> no ceremoniall duty.</p>
            <p>And tythes are no iudicialls, for no iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als were vowed to the Lord as tythes are.<note place="margin">Gen. 28.22.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, Iudicialls are for the ciuill gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of men, and for things in common-Weale.</p>
            <p>Againe, Iudicialls are not holy things,<note place="margin">Leuit. <hi>ibidem.</hi>
               </note> and conſecrated to God as tythes are: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are no Iudicials. If then tythes be neither ceremonials nor Iudicials, they muſt needes be morals, and due by the morall law of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obiectio prima.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Obiections a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this truth anſwered</note> Tythes were dedicated to the <hi>Leuites</hi> for their ſeruice in the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall law; but that law is abrogated: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paying of tythes abrogated.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> The ceremoniall part of the law, which was the aſſignation of tythes to them for their legall ſeruices, <hi>pro tempore,</hi> is abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: but not the morall duty, for that was before <hi>Leuy,</hi> and after <hi>Leuy,</hi> perpetually to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:26209:24"/> continue, and is the Lords right for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>2</label> Tythes are due by mans law, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, ciuill, and canon law: if they were due by Gods law, what neede theſe to ratifie them?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>
               </label> Murder, whoredome, and theft, is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden by mans law; are they therefore not forbidden in Gods law?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiect. </seg>3</label> A competent maintenance is due to Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, but not tythes.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>1</label> Prooue that poſition, for there is no ſuch word as competency in Scriptures ſpoken of; &amp; a fine competent ſort of abſurdities would follow on this opinion. Then we ſhould haue in ſteed of a Biſhop of a Church, a compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencer of a Church; in ſteed of a parſon or Miniſter of ſuch a Church, a competencer of ſuch a Church, a proper title.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Sol. </seg>2</label> Againe, let this competency be granted be it 100 or 200 l. <hi>per annu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> more or leſſe, who ſhold haue the Parſonage? Lay-men, why not Clergy men? But how, by what law ſhould tythes and maintenance bee due? By mans law, by Statute law, ſay they: But may not that be abrogated, and where is that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent maintenance then? So there would be no Miniſters if there were no mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and all the world would grow to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme if there were no Miniſters or learned men to enſtruct the people.</p>
            <p>Theſe are the friuolous obiections of the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:26209:24"/> Atheiſticall ſpirits of our age, that would faine finger our Church-liuings, becauſe they haue found ſweetneſſe, as they thinke, in them already: But yet it hath, and alwayes will proue ratsbane to their ſoules, and their poſterities deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And yet theſe criticall, ſchiſmaticall ſpirits, vnder colour of zeale, and for the maintenance of their owne pride and ambition, would, if they could,<note place="margin">In the ſuruay of the preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded holy diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</note> baniſh thoſe Biſhops which Chriſt and his Apoſtles appointed, and would turne all diſcipline and gouernement vpſide-downe; Churches into Chambers, Biſhops into Syndicks, and Superintendents Miniſters, into Bench-Presbyterians; and would, if they were ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,<note place="margin">Pha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton Ouid.</note> make a new <hi>Metamorphoſis</hi> of the church and Common-weale.</p>
            <p>But here let all thoſe that feare the Lord God of Hoſtes, know, that tythes are due vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Miniſters of the Goſpell by a diuine right, and learne to giue them their dues, leſt that angry curſe of God fall vpon them and their poſterities, which is ſpoken by the Prophet <hi>Malachie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3</note> To be curſed with a curſe for ſpoyling and defrauding the Lord and his Miniſters of their rights: and therefore I will conclude this point with <hi>Moſes,</hi> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing <hi>Leuy</hi> and his ſubſtance: <hi>Bleſſe, O Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Leuies ſubſtance, and accept the worke of his hands; ſmite through the loynes of them that riſe vp againſt him, and of them that hate them, that
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:26209:25"/> they riſe not againe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4 Cir.</note>The fourth and laſt circumſtance to bee conſidered in this text, touching this hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly calling by the Goſpell, is the <hi>terminus ad quem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Text.</note> The period and end of al happineſſe, <hi>To obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Laſt poſition.</note>And heere wee learne, that the glory of Chriſt ſhal be the end and reward of al thoſe that obey the Goſpell: for hereunto hee called you by our Goſpell, to obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. To this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe S. <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith:</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. Iohn 3.2.</note>Dearely beloued, now we are the Sons of God, but yet it doth not appeare what we ſhall be; and we know that when hee ſhall appeare, we ſhall be like him, for wee ſhall ſee him as he is.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.30.</note>And againe, Whom he ſanctified them he glorified: and here in the text, We ſhall obtaine the glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
               </label> But how is this his glory our glory?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> It is his glory and our glory alſo: It is his glory as he is the Head; it is our glory, as we are his members, and haue vnion &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the head. It is his glory, as he is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Head of the Corner. It is our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as we are <hi>ex aedificij latere,</hi> of the building belonging to that Head.</p>
            <p>It is true then, that wee are called by his Goſpell in this world, to obtaine his glory in the life to come; which glory of Chriſt is his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:26209:25"/> by inheritance: it is ours by his merits. And the glory of Chriſt is ſeene in three thing: <hi>In eminentia, in praeeminentia, in coeminentia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aquin. in Cant.</note> 
               <hi>in eminentia coeli, in praeeminentia Angeli, in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminentia Patris excelſi; In eminentia coeli, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius fruitur claritate; in praeeminentia Angeli, quem praecedit dignitate; in coeminentia Patris excelſi, cui aequalis eſt Maieſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The glory of Chriſt is illuſtrious in his eminency, in his preheminency, in his coeminency; in his eminency of heauen, in his preheminency of Angels, in coeminency with his Father: in his eminency of heauen whoſe glory hee doth enioy;<note place="margin">Heb. 1</note> in his prehemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of the Angels, whom he excells in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; in his coeminency with the Father, with whom he is equall in Maieſty. For <hi>Ego et Pater vnum ſumus,</hi> I &amp; the Father am one;<note place="margin">Iohn 10.</note> and to the participation of his glory wee are called, and to his eternall: glory and here in the text, to obtaine the glory of euerlaſting life,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.10.</note> and to haue communion with our Lord Ieſus Chriſt in his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Now as concerning this great and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous place, the Kingdome of Heauen, there are many great and excellent Titles and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes giuen vnto it in holy Scripture, to expreſſe the glory therein contained; but yet none beyond this here in the text: It is called a Life, a Kingdome, an Inheritance, &amp; a Glory. A Life,<note place="margin">Iohn 5.24.</note> and ſuch a life as is not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:26209:26"/> to death; a Kingdome, and ſuch a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that cannot be ſhaken.<note place="margin">Luke 12.32.</note> Feare not lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Flocke, it is your Fathers pleaſure to giue you a Kingdome: There can be no ruine or deuaſtation. Great earthly ſtates are ſubiect to change, and alteration by priuate ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or publike hoſtility, according to that of the <hi>Poet:</hi>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Hor. Ode. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note>Saepius ventis agitatur ingens</l>
                  <l>Pinus, et celſae grauiore caſu</l>
                  <l>Decidunt turres: feriunt<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſummos fulmina montes.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Which verſes may thus be turned:
<q>
                  <l>To ſtormy tempeſts ſubiect are</l>
                  <l>the Pine and Cedar tall,</l>
                  <l>The turrets high as mountaines by,</l>
                  <l>are ſubiect to a fall.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For in all the Antiquaries it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan. 2.</hi> Iuſtine: Sleydan de quatuor Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchijs.</note> that earthly eſtates are moſt ſubiect to change, and are often times ouerturned, and tranſlated to others, as we ſee it come to paſſe in all the foure Monarchies.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Caron Chron.</note>
               <hi>Aſtyages</hi> the laſt of the <hi>Medes,</hi> ouercome by <hi>Cyrus</hi> the firſt Monarke of the <hi>Perſians; Darius vltimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2. Dan. 6.</note> the laſt of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by <hi>Alexander</hi> the firſt Monarke of the <hi>Greekes.</hi> The Monarchie of the <hi>Greekes</hi> ſoone
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:26209:26"/> mangled and rent in pieces by the Feffees of <hi>Alexander, Seleucus, Ptolomie, Antigonus,</hi> and <hi>Caſſander;</hi> who making warre each on other, were at length ouercome by the <hi>Romans:</hi> firſt in the perſon of <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> who aimed at a Monarchie; and then afterward in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Octauius Auguſtus;</hi> who eſtabliſhed the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Monarchie of the <hi>Romans</hi> though not worthy of that Title,<note place="margin">Amand. Polan. in Dan cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> neither doth <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus Polanus</hi> vpon <hi>Daniel,</hi> allow thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the tyranny done to the Saints of God, in the time of the Primitiue Church, vntill the time of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great; the ſame being alſo diuided amongſt the three ſons of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the elder, <hi>Conſtans,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantius:</hi> They peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed all by vnnaturall diſſenſion, and ſo it became deuolute to <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate, Nephew, and ſiſters ſonne vnto <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great.</p>
            <p>Afterwards it was oftentimes oppreſſed by the <hi>Arians,</hi> and other heretikes: ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a great part thereof vſurped by <hi>Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>met</hi> and the <hi>Turkes:</hi> ſometimes diſordered and diminiſhed by the power of vſurped tranſcendency: ſometimes tranſlated from the <hi>Greekes</hi> to the <hi>French,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caron Chron. De quarta Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchia.</note> as in the perſon of <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, the ſonne of <hi>Pipine</hi> the V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurper; afterward became electiue in the time of <hi>Otho</hi> the third, for want of iſſue male:
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:26209:27"/> and at length that ſame <hi>Lapis abſciſſus è mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ſine manibus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2.24.</note> That ſtone that is cut out of the Mountaine without hands, ſhall daſh all theſe earthly Kingdomes in pieces:<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> For it ſhal ſtrike the Image vpon the feete that are of iron and clay, and breake them in pieces like a potters veſſell.<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But this Kingdome of Glory that is here ſpoken of in my text, ſhall neuer bee ſhaken, ſhall neuer bee ſubiect to any deuaſtation, change or alteration.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is called an Inheritance, and an Inheritance immortall,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.4.</note> vndefiled, and that fadeth not away, but which is reſerued for vs in heauen.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it is called a glory, and ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.8.</note> as is a Crowne of Glory. Now what is it that we can deſire that Here we haue not? Doe wee deſire a life? Here it is, and ſuch a life, as is not ſubiect to death: Doe we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a Kingdome? Here it is, and ſuch a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome that cannot bee ſhaken. Do we deſire an inheritance or a glory? Here they are all, aboue all that can be either wiſhed or deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.<note place="margin">Aug. lib. de Trip. habit.</note> For <hi>regnum Dei eſt plenum lucis, laetitiae, beatitudinis et gloriae, quod nec dici nec ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogitari poteſt:</hi> The Kingdome of heauen is full of light, ioy, bleſſedneſſe, &amp; glory, which neither can be ſpoken of, nor imagined. And to this glory of Chriſt here in my text we are called: And ſo ſaith S. <hi>Iohn:</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:26209:27"/>
            <p>Dearely beloued,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 3.2.</note> now we are the ſonnes of God; but yet it doth not appeare what we ſhall be; and we know, that when hee ſhall appeare, we ſhall be like him, for wee ſhall ſee him as he is. How ſhall we be like him? Not with a <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ut</hi> of Dignity and Equality in Glory, but of ſimilitude and quality; we ſhall be like him in glory, ſubordinately, becauſe we are heires annexed with him in Glory:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.17.</note> as wee are here annexed with him in ſufferings, we ſhall be there annexed with him in glory: If we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo bee glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with him.</p>
            <p>To conclude this point; If of that earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſuch glorious things were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,<note place="margin">Pſal 87.</note> (Very excellent things are ſpoken of the City of God) how much more glorious things might be ſpoken of that heauenly <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> which is aboue,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> and which is the Mother of vs all? where are ſuch glorious Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, and one God of Glory, <hi>inſtar omnium,</hi> amongſt them all, and aboue them all. Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py are the people that be in ſuch a caſe; yea,<note place="margin">Pſal. 144.</note> bleſſed are the people that haue the Lord for their God. And therefore,<note place="margin">Exhort.</note> ſince Glory ſhall be the end and reward of all thoſe that obey the Goſpel, let vs yeeld our obedience there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto. conſidering on the one ſide what ſhall be the end of thoſe that obey not the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of God; namely,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 4.17.</note> 
               <note place="margin">2. Theſ. 1.17.</note> That he is comming in flaming fire, rendring vengeance vnto ſuch
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:26209:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> as know not God, and which obey not the Goſpell of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. And conſidering alſo on the other ſide, that if our conuerſation bee as it becommeth the Goſpell of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Phil. 1.27.</note> that hee is comming with a reward in his hand, to giue to euery one at his comming,<note place="margin">Reu. 22.</note> a Life, a Kingdome, an Entrance, and a Glory, euen his owne Glory which is ſpoken of heere in the Text.</p>
            <p>Let vs therefore, Beloued, ayme at this Glory, and runne at this marke of Glory with all might and mayne, that is heere ſet before our eyes:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>So runne, that yee may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs not with <hi>Atalanta</hi> bee allured out of the way, by the golden Apples, either of that old crafty <hi>Hippomenes</hi> the Diuell, or which the World, or our owne concupiſcence throwes in our way. Let vs not for all this World,<note place="margin">1. Iohn 2.16.</note> nor for all the things in this World, loſe this place of Glory. But let vs haſten vnto the marke that is heere fixed before our eyes, euen the Glory of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt; where is life without death, Light without darkeneſſe, Ioy without ceaſſing, and Glory without en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
            <p>To which Glory as hee hath called vs heere in his Church Militant, ſo hee bring vs thereunto in the Church Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:26209:28"/> euen for his Sonne Ieſus Chriſt his ſake. To whom, with the Father, and the holy Spirit, bee rendred and aſcribed all Glory, Maieſtie, and Dominion, this day and for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
